a discussion on blocking DHT between
Dave and
Kyle welcome back to the trt and harmone
optimization YouTube channel and we have
two guests today back with us they've
both have been on the channel before
welcome Kyle Gillette and Dave Lee
welcome guys thank you thank you so
today it was actually a topic that was
an ID from one of the viewers on the
channel a discussion on blocking DHD
between Dave and Kyle so um maybe Kyle
explain to us uh what are some good
indications for blocking DHT why would
you do it um and what's your experience
with
that yeah so a few Basics starting out
uh DHT is dihydrotestosterone as most
people that listen to this channel are
probably aware and it is a stronger
Androgen than testosterone you think
about androgenic effects like the
development of secondary sexual
characteristics of Androgen hormones
like testosterone and DHT you think
about the anabolic effects as well it's
not a perfect dichotomy like that but
that's a reasonable way to think about
it and um there's not really a way I
guess blocking DHT some people argue
about semantics when it comes to lipid
so they'll say well don't call it LDL
cholesterol because it's a lipoprotein
so I'm going to kind of do that in this
case and um we can either talk about
blocking the Androgen receptor or we can
talk about blocking the conversion of
testosterone to D HT so what the
commenter had wanted us to talk about
mostly we can go into whatever rabbit
rabbit
Trail conversation leads but um
specifically talking about blocking an
enzyme called five Alpha reductase
there's three of them that we currently
know we used to know of two of them and
there's a couple different medications
like finasteride and dutasteride and
there's also a lot of supplements that
also block these enzymes in various
strengths and ratios
so we can start off with a few things
that we would mostly agree on is that in
most cases for males and for females you
don't want to do things that block the
Androgen receptor unless you absolutely
have to metastatic highgrade high glein
score which is just aggressive prostate
cancer is sometimes one of those reasons
and then you can block it in various
tissues with sarms as well and then we
can also start with something else that
we would also um probably agree with is
um you want to think about each
individual
cell um as a part of uh physiology
together and independently the word for
this is intracrinology because when
you're talking about five Alpha
reductase Inhibitors you're not really
talking about blood DHT levels or serum
DHT levels you're thinking about its
effect in each organ system in the
body all right um
Dave yeah so firstly um big thank you to
kyl for coming on and talking about this
I know that a lot of people have been
wanting to hear I guess a informed and
uh respectful conversation from both
sides of Defense um I find that that is
often a paradigm that is immensely
lacking in many online communities and I
think the value that people are going to
be able to take away from this is to be
able to have an informed opinion about a
medication they may already be taking or
may be thinking about taking and I think
if the recent years have taught us
anything it's the importance of informed
consent when it comes to taking
medications and um I I try not to be
dogmatic in approaches but um I'm a
little bit dogmatic on this approach but
I'm also of The Stance uh firm beliefs
held Loosely as oppos as opposed to
loose beliefs held firmly which I think
a lot of people have I am very open to
changing my mind recently I had a great
topic with a memo from marck Health
about um the potential uses use cases
for enomy um and I was actually you know
convinced on that which was something
that I've been quite
um I guess ignorant to in terms of to
use a correct uh term for that so my
Approach for I guess the Nuance when it
comes to discussing five Alpha reduct
days Inhibitors I would argue there's
probably three potential use cases for
them one is around hairloss preventing
hair loss which I think most people on
the channel are probably going to be
looking at the second would be as a
prostate cancer profilaxis and then the
third would be for treating prostate
cancer that has already been developed I
have very little understanding and I
would argue no place talking about the
third um it's not in my wheelhouse um
and I'm not going to pretend that it is
um I think it's very Unbecoming when
people speak outside of their Lane so I
don't want to do the same thing um my I
guess perspective on DHT and I'm going
to start this actually when we uh I need
to grab my phone to do that I was
devastated when I lost my hair um it was
one of the most difficult things I went
through in my early 20s but it certainly
wasn't one of the most difficult things
I went through in my life at the time it
was though because I was very young I
was in a band I had long hair I used to
straighten it and dye it I I cried the
day I went to the barber and had to
shave it off it was very difficult so
for people who have the perspective that
you know some people are more attached
to their hair than others I was very
attached to M and I'll put some I'll
send Steven some videos he can photos
maybe you can put up on the so I think
that when guys are looking at using a
five Alpha reductor inhibitor to block
five Alpha reduct days which doesn't
just block the production of DHT it also
five Alpha reduct days does other things
in the body it's important for
degradating cortisol into di hydroc
cortisol so it can be a eliminated it's
important for the production of Alo
pregnanolone as well as the metabolites
of DHD which is 3 a I'm probably
pronouncing this wrong andr stain deal
and 3B andain deal as well which all
have important biological functions and
I would like people to be able to make
the informed decision as to whether the
benefit of keeping their hair for the
Cosmetic and potential psychological
implications that come with that it's an
uncomfortable thing to go through Haas
is worth the potential ramifications and
rep uh repercussions for their
biological Health potentially if there
can be issues where after discontinuing
the medication the side effects may not
resolve which is this syndrome known as
post finasterid syndrome which some
people debate about um I guess the the
most important kind of overarching point
that I would like to address today is
that my concern is that if someone
doesn't have acute effects from using a
fire Bal reductive inhibitor for hair
loss let's say they're like well my
libido is good like you know I don't
really have any problems is that
potentially going to lead to health
ramifications long term that they might
not be aware of you know things
happening now that could be causing
problems
Downstream I think that's worth looking
at
and I guess
overall the importance of guys
understanding what the prevalence of
these side effects are what the
different uh percentages are in terms of
how often they come up I've seen some
people say it's 1% 2% of guys get side
effects in some studies it's up to 15%
get erectile
dysfunction but the other side of the
coin and Kyle did a great video the
other day on uh gop1 and he said he he
gave this perspective of saying well if
there are risks to using GOP ons those
risks are likely outweighed by the
benefits of resolving obesity due to the
risks that come with obesity in these
contexts and I think that that's a very
valid counterargument for using
Pharmaceuticals I would just be
concerned that healthy men sabotaging
their health and for the sake of
something that's not actually
life-threatening that's just
psychologically uncomfortable so that's
my perspective on that and then I also I
guess question whether the you the
benefit of blocking five Alpha reduct
days for the potential development of
prostate cancer is warranted and if is
as beneficial as stated and we can go
through the trials which they have
assessed
that yeah on the channel we have
discussed with several people this post
fenite syndrome uh yeah with a lot of
long-term side effects and ramifications
for them um but yeah Carl you prescribe
it for man with hair loss you still
do I I I don't dare to prescribe it
anymore yeah rarely I will prescribe
finasteride in some cases but uh for
most individuals I prescribe oral
dutasteride or topical dutasteride and
often there is benefits other than hair
loss for
example they might be on a
non-physiologic andren regimen which all
andren regimens including testosterone
creams and gels are non-physiologic
unless someone's applying the cream as
you sleep but uh but occasionally there
is a secondary benefit for example less
DHT driving
erythrocytosis or less DHT driving left
ventricular or right ventricular
hypertrophy or um the prostate benefits
that we have previously mentioned but
the way that I prescribe it I don't know
if you guys are familiar with bipolar
Androgen
therapy no bipolar Androgen therapy is
used for castration resistant prostate
cancer which is kind of like
um inverse finasteride or dutasteride
syndrome where there's a patient that
has prostate cancer they've been
chemically castrated and uh perhaps
they've even taken an adrenal Stog
Genesis Cascade inhibitor as well and it
has um continue to progress and they
actually use super physiologic doses of
androgens like a steroid cycle and a lot
of the same phenomenon happens that you
see in males that take steroid cycles
they take 400 milligrams and then that
reent and they actually continue to give
them 400 milligrams of usually T
testosterone cypionate or an anate so
half lifee a little less than a week and
um they give them one intramuscular
injection every 28 days so they
purposefully Spike up the testosterone
and DHD super physiologically even in
patients with prostate cancer and they
continue to do that until there is
progression of disease because of the
androgens
so they've
resensitized this patient's tissue
prostate tissue in this case but other
genit urinary syndrome tissues can be
resensitized as we do in patients I
think we all take care of or at least
Dave and I take care of a lot of
patients with postf finasterid syndrome
as we do similarly in those cases in
various ways and then as soon as there's
progression then they end the bipolar
Androgen therapy so you can do it the
opposite way rather than give them super
physiologic androgens
let's say there's a patient that is on
um you know they've discussed with their
physician the risk and the benefits of a
higher than physiologic range
testosterone replacement protocol for
example 200 milligrams of cream or gel
per day or 200 milligrams of injectable
or subcutaneous testosterone per week
and they want to attenuate some of those
side effects because they are having
benefits let's say their profession
requires them to continue to do so maybe
they're a strong man competitor and for
the same reason why you do the shared
decision- making process which is the
same way I approach it risk and benefits
as Dave mentioned um the same way that
you have that conversation regarding
their testosterone replacement therapy
or the various options regarding that
you have that same conversation
regarding adding in a five Alpha
reductase inhibitor maybe it is um you
know maybe it's one pill once a week and
then you take a month off that's your um
you know one month on one month off and
then during the month off that's kind of
your uh or two weeks off that's where
your um androgenic total androgenic load
or Androgen pool um as I call it is
quite high and then you're resensitized
purposely to androgens during that
point what do you think Dave could K
convince you to um advise men to take a
a DHD blocker again
when I've reviewed I think one of the
limitations that we have in most Fields
regarding relatively novel
Pharmaceuticals is that we don't have
lifelong or you know more than 10year
follow-up studies where they look at a
guy's overall health outcome so we tend
to look at a couple of variables over a
couple of years or we look at a couple
of variables over 10 years but it's not
like we're running you know these
Comprehensive Health panels and doing
this thorough investigation as to what
happens
and I think one of the contested points
in the hormone replacement therapy space
is DHT as a paracrine hormone and the
impact of circulating DHT on on prostate
cells um there's a study uh titled
dihydrotestosterone Administration does
not increase intraprostatic antigen
concentrations or Ulta prostate antigen
action in healthy men a randomized
control trial if people want to look it
up um essentially they took it was
double blind randomized Placebo control
they took 31 healthy men between 35 and
55 and they gave them super
physiological DHT Levels by by gel so
Sevenfold increase to Baseline levels um
and the findings were uh quote robust
superphysiological increases in serum
DHT um associated with decreased serum
testosterone because they didn't give
them testosterone as well just THD so
shut down as production uh do not
significantly alter in prostatic levels
of DHT testosterone or prostate
epithelial cell Androgen regulated gene
expression in healthy men
PG
decreased shpg delivers androgens into
the prostate so if you give a dhp gel
it'll bind into the liver first decrease
shbg production and not be delivered to
the
prostate does it decrease it down to the
point that it wouldn't deliver any to
the prostate though at least a A
noninferior or nonstatistically
significant amount I doubt the prostate
shrunk if you uh also account for the
confounding variable of CAG repeat
number and the endogen receptor then
that will also help stratify the
data in fact you can go off PSA and
prostate size if you start a patient on
really any trt regimen and assuming you
don't have them on any sort of
anti-androgen the um increase in PSA and
prostate size is very closely directly
correlated with their CH repeat number
so if both double it's extremely likely
that they're very sensitive
tents and and this is where and this is
one of the it's a great example of that
almost all studies are flawed in some
way um because of exactly what I
mentioned before and what Kyle mentioned
there these these mechanisms but I guess
in terms of and this is why I really
like the study of Science and and this
is where I think you know like like
ourselves and I would hope people
watching can appreciate the the point of
science is not to worship it like a
religion it's to use it as a tool to
help us understand how the world works
um and you know when I look at a paper
this was only a 4-we trial um I have
seen men with you know Sevenfold
increases in DHT using bioidentical DHT
anabolic antigenic steroids and I would
argue that there would still be enough
shbg to at least uh impact the prostate
the fact that there was no change
whatsoever in the prostatic
environment as well as other research
suggesting that the prostate recept the
prostate Androgen receptors saturated a
very low level
I would I guess
question the hypothesis or notion
that modulating DHT levels via using
something like dutasteride or
finasteride on hormone replacement
therapy would be beneficial the other
point that I'd like to reference as well
is regarding uh DHT levels as well as
survivability when it comes to prostate
cancer there's research showing that
lower DHT levels lead to lower
survivability outcomes in terms of it
increases the mortality rate of prostate
cancer and I guess the over I guess
coming back to the original point that I
was looking at and I'm a little bit
biased because I I operate from this
Paradigm that I I don't think healthy
people should take Pharmaceuticals but
that's just that's a that's just a
perspective and approach and there's
obviously exceptions to this and when I
talk about pharmaceuticals I mean
bioidentical hormones don't fall into
that category and it's because I operate
from this parad of guilty until proven
innocent and which you know I think is a
good Paradigm to operate on when it
comes to things that are synthetic but
you know people can disagree on that and
in certain context the benefits outweigh
the risks you know particularly if it's
life-threatening um I guess my concern
would be that if we look at the other
implications of reducing or lowering DHT
in the cell because my understanding of
using finasteride therapeutically for
something like prostate cancer is that
because it's imp impacting five Alpha
reduct days at a cellular level it's
reducing the conversion in every cell
which is leading to a more effective if
that's the goal it's more effective at
reducing the levels because it's not
only working on the circulating levels
it's working on the intracellular
conversion so I guess I would be
wondering if the long-term ramifications
of things like the effect on insulin
sensitivity the congest sorry conject
and potential impacts on things like
neurod degeneration and development of
Alzheimer's um potential impacts on the
thyroid increase in
cortisol as well as the thing that we're
very well aware of which is the
correlation between depression anxiety
uh sexual dysfunction as well as gut
disbiosis which is now a relatively
newly identified phenomenon arguably due
to the impact on Al prant alone if I
guess if
overall it's going to be a net positive
or a net Nega negative for someone who's
healthy and I guess that's the this kind
of overarching kind of Paradigm that I'm
I'm going to keep circling back to is
that if someone's not in a risk factor
for a certain disease and I guess it
would be saying well if they're on trt
does that put them into a risk factor
case of prostate cancer which is I guess
what what kl's argument is um not so
much prostate cancer but erythrocytosis
and left ventricular hypertrophy and
increased thromboxane A2 activity
yeah I think a point of agreement that
we can certainly make I always like to
start from points of agreement and then
you can sort out the Nuance is that tele
medicine clinics should certainly not be
prescribing finasteride with uh with or
without Labs really it's really a
nuanced drug and I can also agree that
if it's solely for cosmetic reasons then
young healthy people or even middle-aged
healthy people should also not be taking
uh five Alpha reductase Inhibitors and I
think this same could be said of trt if
they're young healthy with good
testosterone levels if they're only
taking it for aesthetic reasons they
probably shouldn't take U replacement
medication or five Alpha reductase
Inhibitors um the other point with uh
topical DHT is topical DHT is probably
safer than topical testosterone from a
prostate St standpoint but perhaps not
from a hemat poisa standpoint or a um a
hyper trophic cardiovascular disease
standpoint partly because testosterone
of course also aromatizes and if you
give DHD it decreases the aromatization
of the estrogen and the people who tend
to be the highest risk of the highest
grade prostate cancers again glein score
not to prever the prostate but that's
just literally where we have the most
clinical data is they have a um skewed
ratio part of which is genetic of estrad
alpha to estrad Beta two of the many
receptors that estrogen binds to so if
you have less estrogen combining to that
then DHT actually might be a promising
treatment for lower grade prostate
cancers not as promising as sarms like a
noos sarm in my opinion but perhaps
combined with a noos sarm you use DHT
for the androgenic and sexual health
benefits and also to suppress
testosterone when you don't want to go
on full andren deprivation therapy and
then add in a well tolerated sarm for
the anabolic benefits that DHT might not
give you um one other point with that is
the uh daily finasteride and dutasteride
are also and I'm kind of making Dave's
point for him daily fastrite and
dutasteride have both been associated
with decreased incidences of lowgrade
prostate cancer but significantly
increased incidences of high-grade
prostate cancer so you certainly don't
want to take both of them um
continuously where your Androgen pool is
particularly drained and then again
you're going to get more estrogen
probably 10 to 20%
if you're on daily Administration so I'm
I'm certainly a fan of the pulse
dose for those reasons and then
finally the uh three isoenzymes that we
mentioned earlier one reason that
dutasteride likely is far preferred to
finasteride is finasteride is 50 times
stronger on type three five Alf for duct
taste I can send the chart I've posted
it in a previous podcast at some point
and type three is almost always
upregulated when you do have that
disease State start so maybe there's not
um excess tissue growth I guess maybe we
should talk about the brain because
there's actually really similar changes
in the prefrontal cortex of people's
brains and you don't want to upregulate
that type three five Alpha reductase
that's one of the theories why you can
develop more manic symptoms you think
about um you know someone in the Special
Forces comes home they have a little
PTSD they have muscle wasting they've
worked hard and um you know served their
um overlords For Better or For Worse and
then they come back and instead of doing
you know maybe some ketamine therapy or
whatever counseling um they um take a
whole bunch of anabolic steroids and
then that kickstarts a manic episode
which is a um probably related to that
same process just in the prefrontal
cortex which is the decision-making part
of the
brain yeah I'll just um I'll just
elaborate more on couple of points that
that Kyle made there and um so firstly
when when he was talking about the um
reduction in uh low grade prostate
cancer and the increase in uh severe
prostate cancer there's there's two
trials uh one on finasteride and one on
dutasteride which are like these big
longterm uh so if people want to look it
up the finast tribe one's called the
prostate councel prevention trial and
then the dutas tribe one's called the
reduced trial um similar kind of
outcomes in both the the thing that I
think is interesting when when people
are talking about data is that that what
these studies found was there was about
a I think it's about a 30% give or take
off the top of my head reduction in
prostate cancer from fasad but what I
think people also need to look at is
that that's a difference between 10% and
15% when you're comparing Placebo to
intervention so the first one sounds
like way more significant whereas the
second one's like well that's not
actually that big of a change so data
can can be Mis you know misconstrued
when it's looked at in a certain way but
what they found in the reduced trial was
that there was about a so it's 24.8 so
we're call 25% uh reduction in the
incidence of of prostate cancer with the
F reductor inhibitor but then there was
a 25% increase in highgrade gleon cell
tumors so it was kind of like being like
well there's less chance of getting it
but then if you get it it's going to be
more severe and then the other thing
that's been interesting to look at is
how it impacted mortality longterm and
you know there's some different data
suggesting that it didn't make a
difference and then there's some other
studies suggesting that there's uh
reduced um mortality when it comes to
lower Androgen levels and and and so
forth um so that's that's that that's
that point the point about bcsd is very
interesting and I completely agree that
if you are going to come with someone
who's got PTSD they've likely also got
and Dr Mark Gordon talks about this
fantastically the importance of looking
at pregnant alone and DHEA and these
other neurosteroids in you know veteran
induced PTSD when there's you know
trauma to the head if you come in and
then upregulate and nren production
massively especially if you use these
non-bio identical anabolic steroids you
create this basically environment
exactly what Kyle said that's going to
induce Mania because you're massively
upregulating uh excitatory uh
neurotransmission um and and this is a
huge uh detriment to these guys because
you know particularly if someone has got
PTSD and the mental Health's not good
they're more likely to take uh how do I
put this without getting banned um
long-term solutions for short-term
problems we'll say so all of that stuff
is is completely correct and and the
thing that I think that's interesting
that Kyle's brought up which you know
like we both mentioned before that we
hadn't heard of is this idea of if
something is going to be used this
pulsatile approach is important and when
we look at these studies that's showing
the detriments particularly when we look
at in rats in in finasteride they're
injecting them with the equivalent of
taking like a whole packet at once and
then injecting that um the the doses
they're using are just insane and I
would argue that if you injected
paracetamol with that dose you'd
probably cause any kind of issue as well
I mean there's very few things you could
inject that much of and and not cause a
problem so a lot of the a lot of the
research when it comes to these things
is not using the kind of dosing that
that Kyle is talking about and I think
this is why these discussions are so
important is that is for the sake of
nuance um I I guess the question I'd
like to ask Kyle because I know that
this is going to be the thing that a lot
of people are going to be asking about
and this is the bit that Steven will
probably clip
um does if if a gentleman comes to you
like let's say hypothetically on trt or
aren't on trt if there's a difference
with with those please elaborate who's
you know started to progress with hair
loss let's say mid 20s um and they're
wanting to take some form of 5 Alpha
reductase inhibitor or a combination
with something like topical minoxidil or
whatever um what are your I guess what's
your perspective approach
recommendations on that in terms of um
if they did do that what kind of
protocol would that look like because
I'm assuming for hair loss does that
pulsatile approach is that still
efficacious yeah that's a good question
so the first question is the same
question I'd ask if they came in and
asked and said hey Doc how about some
trt I would say what benefits are you
looking to get from this and then what
have you been experiencing or how has
your life changed or may potentially
change that you can look out of it and
uh depending on the age of the patient
let's say they're a 20-year-old I'm
probably just going to tell them right
off the start um that it's the pretty
much almost no matter what the benefit
is not going to outweigh uh the risk in
a 20-year-old so they can look at other
options and I know we mentioned um you
know DHT Inhibitors or Androgen receptor
blockers um there are lots of promising
candidates that we've gone into that for
the purpose of discussion we don't have
to maybe they look at a topical version
of one of those that is not systemically
absorbed topical finasteride is
systemically absorbed significantly and
topical dutasteride is minimally
systemically absorbed it's very
lipophilic although it has kind of a
borderline particle size but it can
certainly be uh systemically absorbed
quite a bit so you have to be really
careful with the 1% formulations because
if you apply 1% every single day it will
be absorbed which if you're not against
some systemic absorption and that's okay
but then are you really going to pulse
your topical it's getting pretty
complicated but you can use topical
dutasteride because of something called
a dose dependent Half-Life same thing as
Tylenol same thing
as aspirin where you have a different
order pharmacokinetic so basically how
the body breaks down each drug whether
it's a um you know regardless of what
molecule it is your body's going to
break it down in one or multiple ways
and after it reaches a saturation point
it's going to break it down very
slowly example of this if you take um
2.5 milligram capsules of dutasteride
every day its halflife is going to be at
least 12 weeks if you take one 40
milligram dose which is the highest dose
I've seen it studied in humans then its
halflife is going to be even longer than
12 weeks but if you take a a very
minimal amount and again talk to your
doctor about the concentration but in
general uh point 2 five% or less I do
like to prescribe the 1% but then you
dilute it with other things and then
apply let's say half of a milliliter
just in the areas that most need it a
tiny bit but a clinically insignificant
amount is systemically absorbed and
before it's circulated it has already
been broken down because it's broken
down very quickly um in uh very low
doses so uh it it is difficult and most
uh if you're just getting topical
dutasteride or finasteride then it's
probably been prescribed too high and
you almost might as well be on the orals
but I do like topical dutasteride
regimens for some individuals but to be
safe um for cases for example let's say
you're Desiring fertility then I also
recommend not even taking topical
dutasteride during that case and then if
you're on oral dutasteride again kind of
similar to trt if the aesthetic benefit
is a bonus then great we'll kind of add
that to that side of the scale but there
should really be other benefits that
you're looking for which are far more
rare if you're not on a trt
protocol and what what were those other
benefits
be of of taking a five Alpha reductase
inhibitor it would be if your Androgen
pool is high in basically any other
organ system in the body your prefrontal
cortex your liver cardiac tissue skin is
mostly an aesthetic benefit but there is
some benefit to it and uh prostate
tissue um you could probably find a few
other examples but um in general it
would be decreasing the
androgenicity of your um either
extremely naturally high testosterone
some people do have it it's relatively
rare there's actually a a pretty big
YouTuber that is currently being worked
up publicly um but he's not a patient of
mine otherwise I obviously couldn't talk
about it but he's publicly being worked
up for extremely high natural
testosterone levels I want to say 2500
total over 2,000 um so they were
concerned for a a tumor that was
producing it his his YouTube channel
starts with an S and he's a pyromaniac
which kind of makes sense um but uh
anyway it it is rare but it does
happen it reminds me of that uh movie I
can't remember what it's called but it's
when the guy climbed um the El Katan
mountain and he he's free climbing it
and then they looked at his brain and he
didn't have any receptors for cortisol
in his brain I was like well that makes
sense um interesting of course he's a
pyromaniac so what I want to give a bit
more context for people watching and
then I want to ask you a follow-up
question because I think this is
fascinating so um for those who aren't
familiar there was a lawsuit against the
manufacturers of finasteride uh which is
Merc and this was in uh 2016 if people
want to read about it I don't know if
I'm pronouncing this right Ru t r s I'm
going to call it rooters that's probably
wrong I don't care but uh the title is
uh court let Merc hide secrets about a
popular drugs risk if people want to
Google it and you can actually read this
section of the transcript and and what
what the uh the the prosecutor says is
uh quote so you knew internally that
these sexual adverse effects were
prolonged or lengthened or never went
away and that is something that would
impact sales in a negative way right and
the answer was yes um of course the
defendants lawyer objected to the
question uh but it was the um so this
was basically a class action against
finasteride for this post finasteride
syndrome um which the company lost and
had to pay out uh it was 4.3 million and
since then they've had to alter the
package insert to say that side effects
uh will resolved to side effects May
resolve which is you know we we leave
that for another day in terms of how the
pharmaceutical uh business works so I
guess my uh followup question to that
which I I I find this uh
fascinating so is the proposition that
because dutasteride is significantly
less systemically absorbed topically
than finasteride a little bit still goes
in but significantly less because of the
structure of the
molecule and what you're also suggesting
because I don't work with it whatsoever
but it wouldn't surprise me that the
dose is being used used on average would
be far too high because of the amount of
nuance in this I guess what I'm
questioning is and I I don't want to
make this like a a uh a black and white
question but this is kind of the
questions that I think people are going
to have so I'd like to ask it would the
idea be that obviously using topical
dutasteride versus topical finasteride
let's say if you had a probability of
developing side effects and permanent
side effects is the argument that I I
guess the argument that most people
agree on is that dutasteride will have a
lower risk than finasteride if an
appropriate dose is used and then is I
guess the question that I'm saying is if
someone is using this like absolute
minimal effective dose of dutasteride in
the kind of dosing regimen that you're
talking about and and the the the form
that you're talking about I'm sure that
you couldn't say that and obviously you
can't say we could guarantee that you
could never get posten asterid Syndrome
from that but I guess the question is
would the odds be so significantly
reduced that it be becomes a virtually
nonrisk factor or such a lowrisk factor
that it's not worth worrying about or
significantly less to worry about would
be my
question yeah that's a good question of
the relatively large number of patients
I've had on oral and topical dutasteride
including patients with uh post
finasteride syndrome and uh because it
can be used to treat post-finasteride
syndrome because it's essentially it's
not exactly the opposite of finasteride
but it is about 50 times stronger on
enzyme type 3 and it's about 11 times
stronger on enzyme type one and
finasteride is at least four times
stronger on enzyme type two so let's say
you decrease the dose by 10 x of the
dutasteride which is kind of what we
done did it's about the same on type one
and I can also send you a chart where
you can put up where the enzymes are
concentrated to make it more complicated
it's not like the prostate is pure type
three and hair is pure and the hair
follicle is pure type two and pubic skin
is pure type two and non- pubic skin is
pure type one but we can send that just
for reference but it's a bit esoteric I
guess to answer the question more
directly is side effects still do happen
if someone's let's say someone's on a
pretty high dose of topical dutasteride
or a moderate dose of oral dutasteride
then often they get um side effects like
low libido I haven't seen OCD or a lot
of the mental side effects other within
the libido and drive where I have seen
those with
finasteride not necessarily inducing a
true OCD disorder but um you know moving
someone further to the Spectrum maybe
it's technically more
ocpd be the classification and then that
can resolve so don't really see that
with dutasteride but side effects
certainly do
occur but the incidence of side effects
as you mentioned is low enough to where
uh treatment is reasonable in a lot of
individuals especially individuals on
trt and especially females too I know
we're concentrated on trt in males um
but there uh that's kind of a whole
another discussion which maybe we do
have at some point that would be
fun yeah this is fascinating because I
think what one thing that I've I guess
haven't articulated well in my uh
critical stance of of finasteride is
that and I I like to relate this to the
I'm going to use the vegan argument as
an example and I I don't endorse a
plant-based diet but I think there's a
big difference between someone sitting
here who's a vegan saying this is why
you shouldn't eat meat versus coming up
to them in a restaurant and taking the
meat off the plate it's two very
different things so I think when I'm
saying you know people shouldn't be
taking this it's like you can do
whatever you want I mean it's just an
opinion and it's a it's a it's a
perspective but I think the most
important thing is that for guys who are
going to go hey I recognize that this
this there's risks here um because I
think with all medical interventions
there are risks especially things like
surgeries and trt as well um it's not
none of these are Perfect Solutions um
they're all imperfect Solutions um and
I'm sure they'll get better as time goes
on I'm sure hopefully one day we'll find
a way to do TRD without shutting down
natural production and I think the most
important thing for guys who are going
to be like hey I'm going to do this
anyway like I had a client the other day
who's like he's like I'm a model I'm a
career model like I can't lose my hair
and I'm like like there are instances
where it's like okay we we have
situations where something has to be
done I think it's so important that
rather than being like never do anything
ever being like if you are going to do
something then this is what you should
do due to XYZ reasons and reducing the I
guess increasing the reward and reducing
the risk in terms of the ratio between
the two as long as there's that
understanding that there is still a a
risk and so forth um you brought up um
the behavioral components of the uh five
Al reduct days inhibition uh
particularly you know high level
systemically in the brain and I'm quite
interested in in neurosteroids because I
previously Had a Brain Injury so it was
a big part of my recovery and um I find
it interesting when when I speak to
people who are very Pro for aside and
often quite belligerent um I find it
interesting when I look at the
mechanisms and try to you know kind of
correlate this between the behavior and
it's like well correlation causation and
so forth but I find it interesting that
the two metabolites of DHT which would
then be reduced not only uh promote
Garba a receptor activity which is you
know what benzoa and alcohol work on for
those who who aren't familiar with Garba
a it's your main inhibitory
neurotransmitter as well as Alo
pregnanolone but um when we look at uh
the 3B version of Andre stain Dil it
also uh is responsible for oxytocin
regulation and I think if we look at
that as well as the potential down
regulation of cortisol metabolism
someone's more stressed less oxytocin
less GBA I think that would lead
behaviorally to the kind of tendencies
that you talked about as well as
increased anxiety and then people
arguing this is also what's causing the
issues in the gut which could be then
having the feedback with the brain and
so forth so that stuff all all makes a
lot of sense
um a couple of other questions that I I
have personally and I guess that other
people would
have when it comes to post finasterid
syndrome I haven't found personally and
again I I haven't been working with
these like I guess I'll call like micro
do of topical dutas that you're talking
about and I'm sure that when I inherit
people who've been using it they're
probably using a lot
more do you think and again I've looked
into this and no one knows so it's all
opinion based do you think that it's a
dose threshold that causes an issue
whether it's from uh time medicated or
threshold you know Peak uh
concentrations or do you think it's like
a genetic interaction that some people
like why do you think some people get
this and some people don't I don't think
there's a specific dose threshold um
there's a lot of interesting effects of
both neurosteroid androgens and
progestogens which are basically just
Downstream of testosterone DHD and
downstream of
progesterone um pregnanolone converts to
can convert some to Progesterone which
converts to five Alpha reduced and five
Alpha and three Alpha reduced
progestogen as you mentioned which is
just the same thing as Alo pregnanolone
and ISO Alor pregnanolone
but I um if if you look at males and
their testosterone levels many people
that have a total te of 250 have no
symptoms whatsoever and there are also
males that have a much higher
testosterone levels that do have
hypogonadal symptoms so the there's a
lot more genetic
variability so there's not a specific
threshold I think of that as the terrain
um and let's if we dial into the central
nervous system the Trin in everyone is
different some people are more
mountainous it's easier to Dam up and
what five Alpha reductase Inhibitors do
in different ways is Dam up different
valleys so finasteride mostly dams up
the type two isoenzyme Valley and
dutasteride mostly end dams up the type
one oddly enough so when you take it an
oral capsule it goes through the liver
kind of first past metabolism and that's
where a lot of five Alpha reduction
happens um that's why oral uh
progesterone and Pregnant alone are both
five Alp reduced in the liver and my
oral pregnanolone supplementation we do
know that it leads to higher levels of
neurosteroid prestant in the CSF fluid
which is the fluid around the spine of
the brain so You' think that dutasteride
stronger but even at a relatively high
dose um dutasteride in animal models did
not lead to as much lowering as
finasteride which is interesting so if
you use even lower amounts of
dutasteride that dam is not so high ey
to where you completely dry out things
and then make that territory of the
brain hyper sensitive to your
neurosteroid androgens and neurosteroid
progestogens and a lot of people mention
EGF when it comes to bodybuilding and
DHT because there's studies where DHT
activates EGF just how uh five Alpha and
three Alpha um reduced U you know if you
look at the progestogens one of them um
is going to activate Gaba a and one of
them actually inactivates Gaba a so I
think of Alo prag nanone and ISO Alo
pregnanolone similar to T3 and reverse
T3 however you have with T4 you can just
form T3 or reverse T3 without going
through one um with progesterone you
have to five Alpha reduce one of them
you can't five Alpha reduce and three
Alpha reduce at the same time there has
to be a stepwise progression so first
Dam to get over when it comes to
neurosteroid
progestins if you slowly Dam up those
progestins and then you let um those
progestogens through from time to time
periodically then you're not going to
dry out and change the territory of
whatever your genetic terrain is
regardless of how high that terrain is
genetically to get over and then to your
other point um at at the end of the day
we are organic machine kind of
regardless of what your spiritual or
metaphysical
self-actualization uh thoughts are so I
think it is reasonable to try our best
to get an idea of how our organic
Machines are made um just like and this
is I think everything you said was
spoton by the way I really liked how you
said there's a difference between the
vegans telling other people to do
something and just like someone that has
you know a car hobby they might say
everyone should put a Turbocharger and
nitrous on their car because it's
literally better and just get your labs
and go to the mechanic and there's going
to be nothing bad that happens it's just
a little bit of money and they say
everyone should have a spoiler and they
should have a new paint job on their car
um and it's kind of the same thing when
it comes to hair and Aesthetics it's
like a car hobbyist arguing about
whether or not you need a paint job or
don't need a paint job so I think that's
a reasonable approach to where if
someone has a strong goal then um you
work with what their desire
is yeah
yeah great
explanation um wise words anything to
add there
Dave not a whole lot to be honest I
think that it's um I think when it when
it comes to these perspectives there's
so much Nuance that's lost when things
get oversimplified um and when things
aren't looked at Case by case and I
think I think you know one of the reason
why you know Kyle and I are friends and
why I've been referring to Kyle for for
patience for for many years now
is when you work in the field and listen
to the people that you're working with
and actually listen to them we all kind
of tend to come to the same conclusions
about things because what is real is
what is real um otherwise it's just
delusional we not listening to things
and I think
that when there's recognition that
there's I I like to look
at I like to look at five Alpha reduct
days inhibition like playing Russian
roulette and depending on what form
you're going to use the more bullets
there are in the chamber so if you're
going to take like high do oral
finasteride versus micro do topical
dutasteride you're looking at a very
different of your odds of having side
effects um but as long as people are
still and and maybe and this is the
thing that I am um I guess that I've
learned tonight which I I very much uh
value is that potentially it can be done
in a way where it might not even be
Russian Roulette if you get hit by a
bullet because if the when I look at you
know the analogy of Russian Roulette I'm
talking about posten asterid syndrome in
terms of like having side effects that
don't resolve because you know Kyle's
seen it I've seen it it's life bruining
and that's a very serious thing but if
there is a way to um if if there is
actually a way to have the cake and eat
it to with this uh medication approach
to the point that side effect risk is so
negligible that it would be comparable
with you know having a couple of beers a
week or you know taking paraso and stuff
like that if if if the risk can become
so
low I think that that's you know not
only a Testament to the work that K was
doing in the field in terms of thinking
critically and actually looking at
things and you know actually working out
how this stuff works and applying it but
it it may also give a really promising
Prospect to guys who need to
psychologically have something done to
manage their hair loss and I think
that's fascinating and it's something
that I'm very excited to look more into
um and the thing that I would encourage
people who've you know made it this far
and listen to the whole conversation is
looking at it and going okay well there
are still risks to all of these things
um but if they can be minimized to the
point that they're so low and someone's
comfortable with taking that risk and
working with a pro and this is the
biggest thing I'm going to say here is
work with a provider who can supervise
this because like this is I haven't
heard of this approach before so if
someone came to me being like how could
I micro do dester I'd like I don't have
a [__] clue you need to book with
Kyle um this is the kind of thing that's
really important is if people are going
to go down this approach that you need
to work with someone who's got the
experience and perspective to be able to
do this properly don't copy and paste
this and do it with your windmill clinic
and think it's going to work out because
there's probably a bunch of testing that
Kyle referred to before that is nuanced
in in terms of whether this approach is
going to work for you so i' I've been
saying for a long time that the the
person who comes up with the side effect
free way to cure hair loss is going to
be a very wealthy map so if if this in
fact if if if Kyle has been able to find
a way to make these medications
significantly more tolerated to the
point that the risk is so minimal that
it's not a concern and it can still
confer efficacy I think that's a huge
Testament to his work as a professional
it's very exciting for the space and I
would hope that more providers will at
least catch on to using the minimal
effective dose to then be able to reduce
you know overall Global instances of
side effects so I I don't really have
anything to add it was a fascinating
conversation So yeah thank you thank you
for taking the time out of your schedule
to to talk to us about this yeah thanks
the both of you it was very interesting
I guess lot of viewers will take a lot
of it thank you so much absolutely uh
thank you guys for the opportunity I
always try to apologize for how many
times I talk about the prostate when I
talk about trt and 5 ARs and things like
that so apologies to the listeners that
are not suffering from those issues